welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right let's begin check-ins my
stomach hurts I feel a little jittery
but there's like a calm excitement about
this talk today so welcome to stoah I'm
Peter Lindbergh steward of the stoah and
the snow has a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this moment and today
we're very lucky to have our friend
Jeremy Johnson at the stoah and maybe
gray will do an introduction on Jeremy
and she'll be running the m/c portion of
today so I will allow I'll send it over
to her now and allow her to explain how
that is going to go can you unmute
yourself yeah hi guys
so yeah today I'm gonna be emceeing this
talk with Jeremy Johnson about
liminality Jeremy Johnson is the
co-founder of liminal news which is a
liminal dart news it's a digital
magazine and it's just it's covering all
sorts of strange topics that are
relevant to the matter crisis like
prophecy and the pandemic and the
occults all sorts of this all my
favorite and most spookiest things so
I'm very excited to talk to him he's
very much like interested in things that
are dear to my heart
um I want to ask maybe Jeremy if you
could start by giving us a little bit of
your view on like what liminality is and
why it's important and what it has to do
with the structure of feeling that's
going on underlying this whole
meta-crisis sure thank you for first of
all having me on today it's an honor
maybe gray and Peter both of you it's
been great to get to know you and get
familiar with the stoic community a lot
of great minds here and great people so
yeah I mean just in terms of housing
yeah just in terms of how I understand
the term liminality you know obviously
I'm connecting it to the meta
modern theme of a structure of feeling
right that's the that famous essay notes
on meta modernism and I was really drawn
to the concept of Mattacks met at my
taxi which means sort of being in
between as an ontological state and
that's really something that I explored
in my cyber USA just talking about meta
and modernism and it really sort of
ontologically expresses the feeling that
so much of us have today in terms of
just feeling like so much of what we
were previously standing on in terms of
institutions forms of sense making
understanding self and world time and
space etc are breaking down and there's
no real clear sense of what's emerging
through that there's bits and pieces of
that but even those bits and pieces
right those innovations that were we're
kind of holding with promise also have a
kind of a Janus face nature to them I'm
talking about the internet and digital
technologies and networks etc so it's
just interesting we've seen this kind of
flux of innovations and then those
innovations also kind of being captured
and exacerbating the crisis at the same
time that they're also offering some
kind of promise right so everything's
really wrapped up in this promise in
parellel together and we ourselves I
feel like are in this process of trying
to reorient ontologically towards you
know I could get into this a little bit
but what is the new ontology that the
climate crisis and that this meta crisis
is teaching us right because we can take
in a sort of liminal fashion the same
issue is the same kind of breakdown and
flip that over and consider it from
another angle and see what it actually
is teaching us so that's kind of how I
understand it but liminality also has
kind of them you know this magical
connotation in terms of you know my
colleague Daniel Pinchbeck
talks about this in terms of initiation
and sort of being in a transitional or
liminal state as is part of the process
of transformation right on a both both a
cultural and a purse
all levels so that it's it's factoring
that into you into the equation as well
so it's a being in between and there's a
structure a feeling of being in between
and then we can get into more details in
terms of what that phenomenologically
actually means like what are those
qualities and what is breaking down what
is arising but just to start there yeah
and I don't know if we wanted to just
keep going or if there's more orienting
questions but I could just keep ranting
about that if you have something that's
like alive for you that's like makes
sense to be the next thing to talk about
I'd love to hear what you forgot to say
I was just gonna mention that that that
the founding of them of the magazine is
kind of in this of liminal is sort of in
this extension of you know Daniel was
one of the founders of reality sandwich
magazine and I've always had this
appreciation for what I call just
countercultural media account or
cultural publishing you know there was
disinformation there was the kind of the
high weirdness of mondo mm and did high
frontiers back in the 80s so there's a
kind of an interesting counter cultural
edge between psychedelia consciousness
exploration the occult and magic and
then digital utopianism and cyber
philosophy etc there's just a long
history of that and recently you know
I've just felt and I think it's just
sort of also part of like the pandemic
starting to happen it was just the right
time it was just it just seemed to be
the right time to bring this forward and
start talking about innovation solutions
side real ways of looking at the crisis
and hoping or yielding some kind of
insight in in that fashion so
um yeah I would actually love to hear
more about why you think that liminality
is such an important subject for us to
be talking about during the pandemic
what kind of opportunities do you think
there are that are like unique to this
unprecedented situation that that
liminality is like just Prime's to
unlock the potential in oh great
question great question so a few things
um in one sense and this is what I had
mentioned in the essay
I think liminality is in some way
intrinsic to the emergent ontology and
what I understand to be sort of an
integral ontology the ontology of the
planetary crisis but also of the
Anthropocene so the fact that it is
open-ended and process oriented and
involves time as it's very theme I think
is intrinsic to something that we need
to learn as a culture in terms of
complex dynamical systems living systems
feedback loops I'm very inspired by that
the work of jean gebser who was an
integral philosopher in the mid 20th
century and he writes quite profound and
quite precedently about these themes but
it also it also shows up in various
philosophies like Tim Martin and hyper
objects an object-oriented ontology so
is this theme of being in between is
actually a kind of mode of being that we
are not very used to as a culture in
terms of inhabiting successfully and you
know there's a couple of essays that we
brought on to liminal like I'm thinking
of Matt Segal's essay towards a guy in
reality right where he's talking about
Whitehead and process philosophy and
needing to incorporate a kind of a
process-oriented view of things but what
I like it would heat about what he says
here right is that this process oriented
view is not just something that's human
created but he calls it a kind of a
cosmological power where we derive our
human values from so liminality is just
sort of a gateway concept to begin
talking about
this different mode of thinking and
perception that we really need to learn
very quickly and I would also draw from
McLuhan because McLuhan talks about this
as the kind of um you know when you for
him it was he has a different vocabulary
but it's the sense of needing to bring
all of the different cultural ecologies
all the different modes of human
communication have existed across
thousands of years a whole human history
into the forefront being able to access
all of that in a very pliable way and
then needing to almost be simultaneous
in that sense that the past the present
and the future are in some sense
coexistent with each other like this the
only way to really navigate the
planetary complexity is to inhabit that
mode of being somehow and we're still
learning to do that I think that has so
much to do with what kind of sense
making we're learning today so I don't
know if that's a direct answer but that
all has to do with this theme of
liminality this theme of processes theme
of temp oryx that i think is just
absolutely just so essential to start
exploring yeah I think you're absolutely
right
um one one thing that comes up for me as
you are kind of like delve into that
more is that we do want to be able to
learn these new techniques and like
broaden our repertoire as a collective
intelligence very quickly and I imagine
that one of the things that holds us
back the most from being able to do that
is like a cultural discomfort with
uncertainty I wonder if you could talk a
little bit about how we could work with
liminality and get more comfortable with
the sort of uncertainty that it demands
from us hmm yeah that this is definitely
like Daniel and I talked about this
during a live stream with liminal in
terms of conspiracy theories we want to
and this is I think it's a very natural
reaction to reach for certainty in this
time to collapse a Metanoia
understanding into a paranoiac certainty
right to just kind of go okay it's
really just about this cohort or this
cabal that's what's really going on so I
can understand and now
get that and it's interesting that so
much of the language around conspiracy
theories for instance is very often
concerned with sovereignty concerned
with understanding you know what's
really going on and waking up so to me
like that's just it's it's a very human
reaction to information overload and
complexity but I also think the the
again the the medium in which we're
swimming on the Internet through
Facebook through Twitter we've gotten
very good at creating these networks but
we aren't using them we aren't designing
them for coherence we're designing them
for fragmentation and there's ACMA
socio-economic incentives for that as
well that like let's say Douglas
rushkoff talks about so the media in
which we're swimming in is engendering
this overwhelm right and I think people
are reaching for certainty in that sense
so how do we read how do we get more
comfortable with uncertainty I think
part of this is recognizing those
compulsions and desires for certainty as
we're navigating these media spaces you
know it's it's it's a very internal work
right now but it shouldn't just be that
you know like what we really need to be
doing is designing these spaces with
coherence and human centric principles
in mind and many different theorists are
talking about that I think I would bring
up Michele ballons who's on liminal as
well sort of discussing how to better
utilize peer-to-peer networks and design
them not only socially but also
economically he talks about the Commons
etc and he has he has a fantastic essay
on unlimite Laswell that's a very kind
of gap serían take it's called Corona in
the Commons and that's sort of again
more of the macro perspective of what's
going on but at the heart of it you know
what he's talking about is is really
trying to learn what he calls a
pedagogical catastrophe like take what's
going on and really kind of read into
you so a crisis teaches us what we
haven't been looking at right so how are
we falling how are we collapsing what
are the stressors and what are they
actually teaching us you know
and I bring this into in the terms of in
terms of liminality you know liminality
is a different mode of time you know
it's disruptive in the sense that just
like the pandemic and just like the
protests that are going on right now
there's a certain intensity that comes
to the forefront and especially with the
pandemic the discussion was centered
around this sort of pausing right this
release from the forward motion of our
culture right the momentum of the
forward motion of the machine of
capitalism suddenly it stops and as a
disaster for that machine right so we
begin to ask well why can't we stop why
can't there be a steady-state why can't
there be pauses in that forward momentum
different types of rhythm different
types of time and of course what goes
along with those is different ways of
being in the world so I think the kind
of radical inquiries that we can make in
this crisis are in some sense providing
profoundly valuable insights into you
okay how do we live in an alternative
way right how do we actually step out or
actually imagine something beyond
capitalism right and it's certainly
something that we're exploring at a at
liminal as well right I think that a lot
of aspects of the meta crisis are things
that we really wouldn't have been able
to contemplate before it happened and
it's interesting to me um usually a
cautionary tale is something that the
the characters in the story leave behind
for the people after to try to
understand and do something different
but there's this strange way that the
pandemic has given us a pause where we
the characters in a cautionary tale can
stop and think about what we might be
cautioned about in the tale and see if
we can make a better decision for the
people already in it rather than waiting
for the next generation to try to
understand what this all means um what
do you think we can do right now to stay
open with out like
having too broad of a scope there there
is so much information there is such an
opportunity to be overwhelmed how do we
be more expansive and more exclusive at
the same time yeah great question well I
think that the first thing that you
mentioned is something I take from
McLuhan all the time I use it at the end
of my side-view essay or he's like we
suddenly need to be aware of everything
that is going to happen and all the
consequences of what's going to happen
before it happens and that's just how we
have to navigate the present now I think
that is such a great and he was talking
about that in like the sixties or
seventies right so I think that is such
a great way of thinking of okay how what
is the mode of sense making for human
beings living in the 21st century it is
this different sense of time and system
in ecology in terms of seeing the whole
field of relations but you're right
there can be kind of an overwhelmed with
this right the overwhelm is is well what
is the coherence right is it a meta
system that I need to follow is it a
meta fury that can help me navigate this
is it just this structure of feeling
right but I think we can actually unpack
that structure feeling a little bit
without needing to create a singular
system or singular narrative
what would I go to you anyway is is
anyone who's so I think part of this has
to do with cultivating a kind of an
artistic sensitivity to the present in
understanding where we want to get to in
terms of a better world out of this
crisis navigating out but then also what
the crisis is actually showing us what
that better world can be and it's not
something that is utopian in the
traditional sense of I'm going to
abstractly conceive of a better planet
we're all peaceful but rather let me
really listen to the present and really
listen to the crisis in that pedagogical
sense and hear what it is showing us
right so it's just it's it's revealing
us as a revealing to us the need to be
entering into different modes of time
and space to be pliable to be adaptable
I'm
draw from David Graeber a lot in the
sense of um he talks about how you know
early human societies and the
Paleolithic would would actually be
quite dynamic they would be totalitarian
in one season and then they would flip
it become a gala terian in the other and
agrarian society sometimes would be
profoundly egalitarian rather than
hierarchical so the question of a kind
of the historical question for us is why
have we become so fixed and we clearly
can't be fixed anymore we have to become
dynamic socially politically
economically we have to be pluralistic
and I think part of the problem is we've
become so rigidify door fixated on that
again that very forward motion the
ideological economic industrial forward
motion so what can engender a different
kind of culture that isn't like that
right the crisis is showing us that this
is what is being called forth in the
moment and then I use this as a helpful
frame of reference but bruno latour
talks about in his book down-to-earth
the arc of modernity is over right I am
in that sense is has completed itself
there is no more forward motion and
anyone who's talking about that like
let's continue with progress or let's it
go back to a better time is sort of
stuck in this oscillation that is just
flinging out of this world and what's
really going on the new ontology and the
new subject is being reoriented towards
the terrestrial those are the coming
down to earth so I think any of these
processes that are going hey you know
humans have these innate tendencies
towards mutual aid life and nature is a
process of symbiogenesis right
cooperation and a making with simple
ASIS and the climate crisis is forcing
us to recognize that and realize that it
is the ultimate coming down to earth
becoming terrestrial and the more our
politics and our social systems and our
social imaginary can go in that
direction come back down to earth I
think that's a good coherence that's a
good principle you guys have had on Joe
Brewers work I think what he's doing is
example like how do we live as a society
post capitalism what kind of economics
what kind of literacy in terms of bio
regionalism are we going to need what
does a post-capitalist future actually
look like right so I think there's many
different expressions of that but I
think we can at least go here around
this is this is certainly like what
Jordan Hall is talking about like as big
as the in you know we're bigger than the
Renaissance or Industrial Revolution but
it's a sort of a counter it's kind of a
reversal and so any of these kinds of
themes I think can really help us go
here the massive complexity of what's
going on and actually kind of lean into
certain tendencies that are not abstract
they're concrete these this is the way
you know this is the kind of the
gravitational pull of the present but it
has to begin with the structure or
feeling like like I talked about in my
essay or else we're just going to meta
ourselves out of this world like bruno
latour warns us about so let's go here
but cohere by listening to the present
and listening to what the crisis is
actually showing us how to be it's not
it's not that difficult but it also is
profoundly difficult because I think
we're we find it difficult as moderns to
do that right let alone you know with
the kind of momentum our civilization
has that is acting against this so yes
long story short we have to listen and
be present I think awesome I'm gonna ask
you one more question before I start
calling on people who are putting their
questions in the chat to give you their
questions um for you guys who are
putting questions in the chat just so
you know this is being recorded and
maybe posted on YouTube so if you'd
prefer for me to read your question for
you just leave some sort of an indicator
along with your question and I'm happy
to do that um so yeah I Jeremy my last
question for you before I pass things
off to the collective intelligence a bit
more is how do you think the myth of
stability that has existed around our
social institutions has created like
blind spots that are very you
to this generation mm-hmm the myth of
stability I mean you know I think this
is something you know it's unfortunate
that I talked about this right as the
pandemic was starting like people
started talking about supply chains and
growing gardens and like more and more
people like that the what was seeing as
some hippy utopianism right like okay
yeah there could be a better world but
the the realism of this world is such
that those things are nice ideas that
might kind of work their way into the
center gradually we're suddenly in a
disruptive moment where the center is
just falls out from beneath us and it's
stability it's it's concretion is just
completely in question so the the the
cynical remark about this it's is that
it seems that until the the ground
beneath us falls out in this way the way
that we are living through right now
it doesn't it remains an abstraction it
remains a hypothesis it remains a
daydream or a reverie of the culture to
imagine itself in a better place but
when that stability falls out it's a
false stability and it always has been
it's been very tenuous but when that
falls out I think that's when we begin
to intensify and give permission to
actually rethink the center but it's
very helpful when we have better
coherence about what this new center
could be so I would say there's been a
kind of reversal where the previously
utopian and more beautiful world you
know that Charles Eisenstein talks about
is suddenly like oh that would actually
be great
right now it'd be good to have a back-up
plan for my family because I don't know
or if I could get bread or if gas goes
out or if a supply chain goes out in the
next coming years you know it would be
great to have some kind of alternative
and resilient plan and I think these are
the kind of things as the system systems
buckle and collapse the innovations come
forward like you know we saw this
happening in real time the United States
where the federal answer to the pandemic
was no longer being addressed in terms
of coherence and so local regional
almost Commonwealth started arising
about like how to strategize reopening
or not or how to source the the medical
supplies that they needed so on the one
hand this seems like fragmentation but
on the other again if we take this theme
of a perspective 'ti that gaps your
talks about or Latour is talking about
with the terrestrial that there may be a
better answer in terms of you know
nation-states are perhaps not the best
expression of a planetary polity you
know and decentralization is something
that we actually have to learn now for
the first time we're doing it with
networks and digital culture and
communications but have we really really
reworked society at that fundamental
level we're still using you know you
know a thousand two thousand year old
institutions to think about planetary
dynamics maybe those don't work
maybe our institutions need to reflect
the network's that were communicating in
and the living systems that were
increasingly learning more about so and
that's a bigger like well holy crap
that's like a that's not just a
civilizational turn that's like
ontologically as profound as as what
morton talks about with the the
anthropic seen the human becoming nature
and the nature becoming human and this
is also something that I think both
McLuhan and gaps are talked about in
their own ways but gaps are particularly
really talks about transparency the
supersession of these modernist dualisms
are finally being overcome but the
problem is right the crisis is can we
overcome them will they overcome us can
we outlive the crisis or will it outlive
us and that is immediately and directly
related to what we can draw from what's
going on right now how deeply we can
listen and cohere and respond to it um
you know that was a great question
though I mean this is the question right
this is the question are all trying to
figure out and entertain right now
better hope the internet doesn't I saw
Tom's comment there yeah yeah you know
the interesting Tom and and just a sort
of a comment to you like Willie Marin
Thompson has this concept back in the
70s I think this is great it's from a
little book he wrote called darkness and
scattered scattered light or he pathi
sizes basically in a McLuhan turn a
reversal back to the village but he says
no no this will be the meta industrial
village where localization and
regionalism etc and decentralization
will occur but through digital networks
like we'll be okay we can kind of
retrieve the pre-industrial world in a
kind of new new expression that might be
one model I don't know like but we need
to be considering these kinds of
expressions and models let's still a
village nicepeter anyway I'm sorry I'll
open it up to you to you a facility
these questions uh yeah I I know Peter
had been having to do with liminality
and the sort of memetic environment that
we're in right now if you want to
yourself
cool thanks maybe yeah I wrote it down
um a longer version of it so running
with this concept called
the luminol war and I'm viewing us are
like an upgraded version of the culture
war where it's like this confusing
disorienting hyper fragmented battle of
narratives in this liminal state that
were in and I like what you and maybe
were talking about both building a good
relationship with liminality uncertainty
and knowing this however and there's
like a little war a lot of like mimetic
tribalists that are demanding us to take
a position and even if they're right
proposition lee a lot of them are coming
from a place of having a bad
relationship with uncertainty and like
there's a lot on the line right now you
know there's a meta-crisis an
existential risk law type of stuff but
it's
we're talking about you know this like
building a good relationship Illuminati
or uncertainty people are saying like
you know fuck off you know just take a
side you know like there's no time for
this
so how would you respond to that because
I do agree with you I think this is a
very very important task how do we
cultivate a great relationship with
liminality uncertainty and all this
stuff but at the same time you know
respond to the medic Rice's and sort of
negotiate those relationships if people
are coming to you and you know basically
gas lighting you to take their position
good question and it's something that
I've been thinking a lot about in terms
of some of Kepler's insights on because
he he has a sort of general
understanding of this unfolding of
consciousness with different structures
and they all kind of still play out in
very interesting dynamics and I think
totalization and oppositional ism and
this hyper fragmentation that are that
are again our networks are engendering
to a great extent is unfortunate but in
terms of how to react or how to respond
or cohere with that um I don't think
liminality means not acting or not being
comfortable taking an action that we
would be perceived as a side I think the
real capacity to be liminal is to
actually kind of say yeah I agree with
that or yes I'll take the stance with
you and still render it transparent in a
sense like I'm gonna engage with you
ethically morally because we should and
we ought to I don't agree with the kind
of totalizing way you're coming down on
that but I do agree that you know you're
expressing something let's say I don't
know let's go protest right let's go out
right now let's join we feel our hearts
are calling us to go down and do so
somebody says you have to do it whatever
you know like but go ahead and do it if
you feel called to do it right like I
think this shouldn't hinder us from
having action and then also rendering
those actions transparent the sort of
larger medicines that we're talking
about here right like
I very often talk about this whole
election cycle and during the pandemic
right there are certain policies there
are certain legislative policies that
are being enacted and they're very
polarized in terms of the political
landscape nevertheless I think it's good
to enact and participate without feeling
like we're you know in that sense of
being in the world but not of it you
just have to go forth and do what you
got to do you know so I think for us the
harder part is to participate without
getting stuck or without acquiring the
totalizing perspectives that tend to
crop up everywhere right how do we
navigate that it's very difficult we
have to in a sense be mediators and also
in another sense we have to be kind of
attempting to cohere and render
transparent this larger process and why
we're acting and I think that's a very
difficult task because again our
communication media is just encouraging
us to take a totalizing viewpoint right
it's it's it's wanting us to collapse
complexity into yes or no
can we still say yes or no can we still
act and not collapse into that mentality
it's very difficult right I think this
is at least the start of what we have to
do right like you guys have had a
Michael Brooks on and you know Michael
books is a good is a good friend of mine
and we've talked about this before too
in that sense of you know absolutely
these sort of meta processes are really
important and there's something you can
do right now and actually maybe by
participating in that and leaving the
window open to these sort of more macro
meta perspectives in the communities
you're engaging with that are very hyper
polarized
I don't know maybe some of them will
come on board with that and be more
interested in that because there's a
bigger coherence right there's a bigger
I don't know what we were talking about
before a larger sense of the process
that's happening and how they're a part
of it you know like say yes to them and
show them that they're a part of
something that's just more than you know
the entrenchment of
medic Wars right easier said than done
but I don't see I don't see an end what
do you call it a kind of arrest between
taking an action with a perceived stance
and still being in this liminal space
right if that makes sense
yeah thank you um I think Walter your
your question might be an interesting
place to go from here if you'd like to
unmute yourself Hey thank you this is
kind of a very open-ended question so
please just interpret it however you
want
I was asking some people for example
Erica Legolas in her book of occult
features of anarchism have pointed out
that conspiracy theorizing is more
common among people without college
education and then on the flip side of
that we see sort of a cadet a
credentialism that appears in people
with college degrees where they sort of
have a habit of thinking that if
something was published in a journal or
it comes in a fancy packaging with a lot
of acronyms and stuff that it's true and
it seems like both of those placeholders
are there to avoid saying I don't know
and I'm wondering if your project is in
part we're mostly about finding out more
productive ways of saying I don't know
while still being productive in the
world yeah great question and that's
also a great way to kind of also respond
to Peters inquiry to like I don't know
I'm going to participate I still don't
know right I think that's very helpful
to frame it that way but yeah you know I
think so I mean you know Daniel and I
talked about this in terms of like maybe
part of liminal Zoll as as a media space
in the consciousness culture could be to
help verify and cohere conspiracy
theories and try to avoid the the most
reductionist elements of it while not
necessarily like removing the capacity
of our own you know subjectivity to have
some kind of validity right our own
sites and intuitions and experiences
like it's it's there's no easy answer
but one of the things I do remember
actually from that from that particular
book is that you know sometimes and this
is something Brooks mentions as well by
way of William Aaron Thompson but
sometimes conspiracy theories can be
very interesting if we flip them again
and look at what they're actually you
know implicitly talking about you know
they may be caricatures are sort of
two-dimensional expressions of a very
multi-dimensional and complex process of
power dynamics but they might reveal
something actually about those power
dynamics in a way that is accessible
right and almost folkloric so there's
ways in which we can even be friendly to
these narratives and think about them in
a way that um no I don't know this is
just this is just how I've approached it
in the past I don't know if you know
conspiracy theorists would appreciate
being interpreted in this way and sort
of almost innocence psychologize din
this way but nevertheless I think they
do express something about what's going
on and it should be addressed it's just
sort of done in a very kind of
literalized fashion and so if we can
again hold that lightly and not go along
with the literal isms maybe we can learn
something from a particular conspiracy
theory about I don't know the flagger
there's something along those lines I'm
just bringing up flat-earthers as one of
the more extreme examples but for them
even you know I think that there's this
desire to return to a measurable world
right
a world that can enclose themselves and
there's a sense of a loss of world right
now it would be very good if we could go
back in to the enclosure of the the
unperceptive all dome that they often
talk about so you know these things can
tell us more about our own human
compulsions and desires and we can
sympathise with them but um I don't know
if that's a direct answer to your
question though but uh that was a good
one
I think Rana has a really interesting
question that he's asked me to read on
his behalf he feels that progress and
capitalism for a lot of people are very
tightly associated with freedom and he
wonders how you see a post capitalist
world as compatible with personal
freedom and autonomy rather than then
some song place where we would have to
give that up mmm that's great
yeah so I think we have to of course
think about this in well in in this
sense you know capitalism and modernity
certainly give us this gain which is
this gap stur talks about this all the
time this this new sense of
phenomenology of being a self moving
through the spatial world directing
their will and their reason in their
measurement in a certain sense molding
the world to their their will and
revealing the world in that in that sort
of a go extents it helps shape the self
in that very respectable material sense
there's an autonomy inhalation in that
the the double side to that right the
other side to you modernity and you know
everything that it has brought forth is
a loss of participation in the living
world right there is this freedom and
release you know them Charles Taylor
talks about this as well many different
theorists talk about this right the
sense of the buffering of the self that
emerges through this this newfound
spatial being being an ego
subject-object relationality in duality
and so on but the downside of that is
there's a cutting off of participation
in these other modes of experience that
you know pre-modern times had and then
of course there is the gains in the
losses of actually you know the process
of capitalism and industrialization and
and that the D Village and D cultural
acculturation of the world right the
loss of craftsman the feeling that this
is something I kept sir also talks about
X Manu the emancipate
means out of the hand right what is
being emancipated the self is released
into the world but we've also lost
control of the very those very same
powers that have released us we don't
have autonomy or control over capitalism
seems to be running away right history
over the past two to three hundred years
has been ramping up of temporal
intensity breakthroughs and revolutions
and disruptions so many
twentieth-century theorists talk about
this feeling of kind of being a
whirlwind
I love Liam Gibson's discussion on this
recess like we're in a howling wind
tunnel right and we no longer live in in
a present with a sufficient now to stand
on it's just sort of crisis management
so this in the same freedom of self is
also this same feeling of powerlessness
of the forces that that self is
unleashed so this is again going back to
that sense of liminality like when we
talk about freedom and individual and
modernity and industry we're also
talking about the time crisis the
historical crisis technology runaway the
Anthropocene and the capitalist scene so
they come together they come together so
the question is still here and it's
still present which is okay so we have
the self we don't want to undo it how do
we get past this somehow how do we
supersede the ego and the self and
modernity without necessarily undoing it
and I don't think necessarily that
simple aphorisms of transcendence
include or you know okay let's like fold
that in and move to the next stage those
don't actually answer the question of
how to do that right so I don't know
exactly either but I would say that in
the process of now we're treating this
this orientation of coming down to earth
there's new freedom that's allowed I
mean there's literally existential
freedom from not wiping out humanity
right in in in you know what could very
well be as if we believe what Jim Dell
Jim Bendele is talking about like mass
species die-off that would take us out
in the process so the ego has a right to
exist and civilization perhaps
- but not at the extent our expensive
ecocide and civilizational suicide which
is where we're headed so how do we
overcome the self as the same question
as how do we overcome civilization and
and what the modern self has brought
forward in our time and none of us have
the answer to that but again I think the
answers are appearing in all of these
different modalities all these different
practices and theorists from Brewers
worked and Michele Bauwens work what
gaps are is talking about what the tour
is talking about the coherence and the
thematics are there and I'll just end
with one note on what something take
hard a shirt on often talked about
resale you know in the process of planet
ization the overcoming of the self can't
just be the dissolution it has to be the
Supra personal so where does the
personal and the human and the
individuals be retained in this new
world let's look to that were those
success stories right and again I think
that has to do with being human again
again the pandemic allowed us to take a
breath many of us ironically as it was
taking our breath away in that sense it
allowed us to begin to inhabit modes of
human time rhythmicity being stuck in a
place for a long time with other people
contemplation the slowing down of the
day you know those kinds of very human
things that we had before the one set
the one sided directional you know
modern pace of life really just
totalized everything in mark Fisher's
capitalist realism so okay that's
actually a way to be more human that's a
way that the modern industrial egoic
self lost actually and was in the
process of undoing so it's a very
complicated question about what the
modern self is actually achieving and
how that is very kind of limited right
or fragmented in that sense I don't know
if that if that directly answered that
question or not but
I got a thumbs up from Ron so it looks
like we're good
yeah absolute poetry to me III would
like to hear Jacobs question about
narratives if Jacob would like to unmute
himself maybe he stepped out let's see
who else has a question um Bart it looks
like you also had a question for Jeremy
if you'd like to I'm here yourself yep
hey Jeremy so I heard you mention for
you
you put a Rudolf Steiner quote in the
chat yesterday and I've heard you you
know talking about the idea of reversal
that's kind of an image that I've been
sitting with for a while no but if I've
noticed that the the anthroposophical
kind of thread of thought is like
somehow not finding its way to the game
be conversation and just thinking like
about the idea of the see if I can do
this in a good way like the idea of the
reversal of the fo'c'sle and kind of
this mimetic tribes as like having the
potential to be game be communities and
what what somebody recently told me that
Steiner referred to as new Mike I Alec
communities
yeah good question I am relatively new
to the game B communities like so I
don't really know the ins and the outs
I've really just been exposed a little
bit to you know gym ruts material Jordan
Hall and 'shmock dan berger talking here
and on rebel wisdom and elsewhere but um
yeah i think the part of this right is
is how much of a host materialist or a
materialist phenomenology are we going
to allow ourselves to reintegrate and
remediate I don't think that a
post-capitalist feature that retrieves
the village etc is going to be the same
kind of secular anthropology that
moderns and westerns have been
engendering you know maybe part of them
will you know and maybe game B is more
interested in kind of looking at meta
systemics and game theory etc but part
of this and this is sort of what I
really like that Steiner is bringing up
of course but then gaps are also really
frames very very usefully is a sense of
okay well we are not merely modern sight
there's other modes of being in the
world that continue to persist
interpretive there mutation so the
magical the mythical the soul oriented
the folk oriented all of those
capacities not only continue to exist
but also involve themselves in rational
thinking and in secular culture in a
sort of invisible ways so I'm kind of
interested more in this sort of this
anthropological turning where we're
actually bringing that back in as well
and I don't think everyone needs to in
that sense we all have different
dispositions but I do think that's part
of the part of the story here and only
framing it in terms of kind of systems
thinking and secularity is very kind of
a Western centric modernity centric way
of thinking about this planetary crisis
and
Ellucian whereas you know this look at
the majority of human beings on the
world and on the planet have not been
necessarily secular in that sense and
still today right it's their
transformation to you know it's not just
the secular West's planetary culture so
I think there's a plurality that we have
to consider and certainly like I think
with the consciousness culture obviously
like we talked about Steiner and
psychedelics and spiritual experiences
etc and of course engaging with
indigenous cultures and First Nation
cultures and communities that are still
present today so again I think it's a
more pluralistic universe you know and
that's part of what the turning could be
in that deeply phenomenological sense is
it's it's an overcoming of our own and
this is an inquiry in an invitation for
us I think it's an overcoming of our own
fixation on the phenomenology that has
you know so identified modernity for so
long the spatial orientation and get
into like more of that detail but yeah I
think it's this isn't opening up you
know this is not meta modernity this is
meta something else meta Planetary
planet ization I don't know I don't know
there's no words for it but um I think
part of us is exploring that as well I'm
not sure if that directly answers your
question about game being the
anthroposophical views
awesome we're getting a kind of near the
end so they're probably only be one or
two questions left but I'd be really
interested to hear from Fred about his
question if he'd like to unmute himself
we can't hear you
there you go that should work wheelchair
America know each other because I'm fan
of his Gibbs of course and to me gaps
were a very important thing to say we go
from it's an evolutionary development in
which he says at the moment we go from
the mental to the integral and I feel
that the integral has definitely an
inherent spiritual aspect to it and so
also transparency and also to what
ferritin are part of the failure system
if I look at what is happening with
George Floyd if we want to be present
that's very much what is on each that's
a inner and outer scream it's what I see
definitely by young people is that there
is a very deep feeling of equality that
wants to show up and in that sense this
this the risk is shift from this ratio
thing which has very much to do it's
kind of the white people being very
mental and now shifting to something
that is inviting more a deeper variety
so that's that's what brings me until
the the feeling of why not look at the
aspect of which of the failures that we
see now showed up which i think is
universal love is part of what we are
going and then equality has very
much to do with that and so instead of I
find that don't pray in very difficult
head concepts going into a more feeling
concept of could that be possible that
the human stage that we are coming into
now is hard based from there thats a
different value systems are going to be
lets say created also which will also
deeply affect the let's say that the the
value of what we call you know to be a
genius is being fairly rich what we now
see in the in the crisis is that people
with so-called common professions like
teachers and are seen as well so there's
a deep value shift in those aspect so I
would love to if the liminality is
perhaps also an acknowledgement of the
need for an emotional maturation yeah I
think that that gets to part of the
heart of it right Fred um good question
I think first of all if we take what
gebser says at least and I think other
theorists about cultural evolution
discuss I'm thinking of Ursula K Le
Guin's Lion from one of my favorite
essays by her California's and not on
the euclidean place to be strange title
but where she says you know we've been
so this is just this is the problem
we've been so over oriented towards this
once a sighted fixation towards
abstraction towards the mental towards
spatialization towards sort of a
directed mechanism an industry that has
so much momentum that our our sense
making is so oriented around the mental
it's so fixated that a reversal
is almost it is the intelligence of I
don't know what he would call it of the
itself that kept stir talks about that
is or the dowel I suppose maybe Lagoon
would say that is calling forth a
reversal a reorientation a restructuring
the Alaia if order is is asking of it of
itself right and the crisis is revealing
that of itself that reversal return
release stopover abstracting stop you
know you know that kind of arc of
modernity is being inverted and reversed
in all of its tendencies all of its
sense-making tendencies because it's
been so one-sidedly fixated it's going
to destroy us if we continue that way
and the answer is not to continue
pedaling harder that way either right so
in terms of heart-centered yes but also
and got centered and mind centered like
and this is the whole this is the
McLuhan turn this is the integral turned
with cap sir this is the simultaneity of
all of our cultural modes of expression
and sense making are what the planetary
dynamics of complexity are calling for
it's not just the heart it's also the
gut it's also the mind right there's a
the the idea that the key characteristic
here is bringing that all forth and part
of you think the process today and this
crisis has been the heart because that
does need to be remediated the
human-centric centrism the mutual aid
right that's been a theme of this
pandemic it's been a theme of the of the
riots in the sense it's anger about the
loss of life and the failure of these
institutions to to care right so yeah I
mean that there's this sort of
dehumanization and alienation from self
and other that this form of culture has
so so successfully produced that yes the
reversal is needed but the reversal is
not just an undoing it's a retrieving
and integration and I think that's
that's the the challenge we're trying to
work through because what we see right
now is you know a lot of overemphasis in
some degrees of things that have been
unintegrated that
I've been slapped off that have been
disintegrated and part of that is yes
the Commons human centrism mutual aid a
society that engenders that and values
that at its center those are all things
that are easy enough to cohere about and
go yeah those all need to come back
online I would just say like as a
distinguished as a discernment it's not
just the heart it's the whole being
really that that is being invoked in
this time if we don't respond to the
whole we will be undone by though the
complexity of the whole right like
that's what I'm I'm feeling but
certainly the heart again
certainly the soul again right I don't
know if we want to equate those two but
heart soul and and and a living world
right in every way that means from the
magic and mythic to the the kind of
Sciences that hair away and Lynn
Margulis talk about and Nora Bateson
talks about so yeah could I bring in one
one thing that I I just found let's say
two weeks ago the idea that if we really
look back from let's say evolutionary
point of view we have now and let's say
for the first time we have cosmic
Genesis the biogenesis and with yet
cyril homo genesis stages and I had this
idea of the shift from let's say how
many to the the ape he lives in the
world in which let's say there is very
much the prey and the predator and when
I see the human being kind of
integrating its in itself the prey and
the predator
we are also victims and we are creators
and in a certain sense if you then see
that the feminine could be lets say
related to the prey because the defense
the looking out is it dangerous not
the more oriented this what is possible
there's a completely I feel there's a
very rich thing that comes in us to
connect to the natural world and coming
we are at the top of the hour so I'm
just gonna interject myself now um but I
am happy to keep this space open uh and
hold a sense-making session after for
any of you who do have lingering
questions for now I'm going to toss it
to Peter to say some closing remarks
though thank you maybe and thank you for
the excellent emceeing today this is a
baby's first time seeing she's gonna
have her own series called raw sexuality
here at the stove which were super
stoked for and Jeremy thanks so much for
coming today my friend that was an
awesome talk and then I think I've told
you before when we were corresponding
before this like I'm super open for
collaboration with the stolen liminal
news I was actually thinking of doing
like a Stila like a stoic news channel
every night just to kind of like sense
make what the heck is happening I'm not
watching the news anymore and I get
triggered when I see all these like like
when my body gets hijacked but it'd be
good to have like a calm space we can
actually sense make what's actually
happening there is a nod of the
situation so maybe we can double click
on that later so in a moment I'm gonna
hand it back to Maeby and she's gonna
lead a sense making session I'm gonna
have to leave right now but whoever can
stay here and wants to chat a little bit
more we have the space open for a while
so we can do that just gonna plug a
couple of events that are coming up so
tonight we later today not tonight we
have two events out of our wisdom gym we
have a relational exegesis with Jessica
and that's 4 p.m. Eastern time we're
reading a finite in infinite games with
James cars and the idea of this psycho
tech is building relationship with the
text while we build it with each other
and top secret I'm waving that so top
secret but James cars agreed to come to
the stoah so hopefully we can land a
time here he was on my podcast
previously fucking geek you know but
over that and then we have a shame
breakthrough boot camp with everyone's
favorite shame educator AJ bond that's
at 6:00 p.m. Eastern Time today as well
it's more we have a really cool event
bio emotive framework and introduction
could you introduce that maybe because I
know you've experienced this modality
yeah
tomorrow we have a dog chattering coming
by at 4 p.m. Eastern to talk about his
bio motive framework it's a synthesis of
his like decades of the acronym in
statistical analysis and like clinical
psychological work but it he also has a
really strong grounding in mindfulness
practices and Eastern religious
practices that are being westernized
a lot right now his framework helps you
find core feelings in your emotional
understandings understand the difference
between those and social and survival
emotions helps you update your
impressions update your beliefs about
your own feelings and it helps you fully
experience what your emotions are so
that you don't end up having like these
Wingard half resolved feelings floating
around in your body and waiting down so
I think that it's it's it's just an
amazing amazing process it has
absolutely changed my life it feels
feels so cliche to say that but it this
time is actually true I went through
like profound physical mental spiritual
emotional change in just a weekend of
working with Doug
he feels like a father to me now
actually he just has like that warm dad
energy so if you need some warm dad
energy make sure you so much tomorrow
for sure
beautiful thank you and if you want some
warm mom energy we have rear back who's
come just collective presencing at I
think it's 12 p.m. Eastern Time so yeah
the idea is with this ecology of
practices it's sort of organically
emerging here at the stoah and I'm
really excited about that um I was plug
another in Tison are you are you uh
presentable right now you've got
something that's really related to
today's event on Saturday you're a mute
yeah thanks Peter yeah the event on
Saturday is called flowing with
unknowingness and it's experimenting
with freestyle rap and spoken word as
psycho tech or a practice for deepening
our relationship with uncertainty
through creative self-expression and
then aiming that experience toward
reaching group flow and seeing if we can
create a dialogue amongst us and really
engage that emergent energy through the
form of freestyle it's like dialogue OHS
but it's sort of held and lubricated by
musicality and instrumentals and beats
and it's been a lot of fun for me and
it's a good way for me to learn about
the people in this community
yeah much more deeply totally and maybe
and I can attest as a fucking awesome
psycho tech so the story is based off
the gift economy you can go to this page
if you're inspired to provide a gift to
the stola myself the Stewart or any of
the facilitators here you can go there
and we'd be greatly appreciate your gift
that being said everyone thanks for
coming out today thanks Peter thanks
Jeremy